Now, if you were to take a bunch of
early Americans and cut them open, you'd
find that westward expansion was coded
all the way down to their dang DNA.
After they got metric butt loads of land
in the Treaty of Paris, they thought
that all their westward migration dreams
were coming true. But, here's where I
tell you that it wasn't all puppies and
rainbows, and I reckon we ought to talk
about it. So, if you're ready to get
them brain cows milked, let's get to it.
Okay, now remember that Big Mama Britain
had prohibited westward migration after
the French and Indian War, even though
that victory gave them access to the
oh-so-tasty lands in the Ohio River
Valley. But, after the American
Revolution, all those lands belonged
squarely to the US government, and that
meant that Americans got their migration
on quick, fast, and in a hurry. But,
wait a minute. Why did Big Mama Britain
prevent such migration in the first
place? Well, one of the main reasons was
that the westward movement of the
colonists would for surely lead to
conflicts with the American Indian
groups who already lived there. And
guess what? That reality in no way
changed now that the territory belonged
to the US. So, that means it's time to
talk about how migrating Americans
caused conflict with American Indian
groups. So, not only did Americans want
to migrate west in order to establish
homesteads and get their agriculture on,
they also wanted to prove a point to the
American Indians who lived there. And
that point, my dear pupil, was this. You
see, even though the British and the
Spanish maintained a presence in the
western territory, Americans were keen
to migrate and settle there in order to
convince the American Indians that the
land belonged to them and not to the
European powers. And so, as Americans
migrated and settled, often without
legal ownership of the land, American
Indians were displaced and were forced
onto smaller and smaller tracts of land.
But, the American Indians didn't just
roll over and accept this intrusion. No,
the massive wave of migrants resulted in
new American Indian alliances
coordinated to resist the migration of
white settlers. And to put it mildly,
clashes occurred to the great vexation
of American settlers. At which point,
Big Mama Britain, scorned but by no
means less sassy, was like, "Huh, how
y'all like me now?" Anyway, all of this
was going on during the era of the
Articles of Confederation, and because
the federal government was about as weak
as the fruit flavor in a can of LaCroix,
there was almost nothing they could do
to effectively address the growing
tension. However, once the articles were
tossed and the Constitution was
ratified, the federal government flexed
its new muscles and attempted to solve
the problems which migration had caused
with American Indians. Now, one of the
first laws passed was the Indian Trade
and Intercourse Act of 1790.
Essentially, the law made it the
prerogative of the federal government to
regulate settlement of the western
territory of the United States and to
make sure that American Indians were
treated fairly in the process. Oh, wow,
that feels really good. Like, I'm so
glad that American Indians, after having
been so long treated poorly by the
Americans and their government, are
going to receive some equitable
dealings.
Okay, I'm getting word that American
settlers basically just ignored that law
and continued to push westward, which
intensified the conflict with American
Indian groups all the more. So, you
know,
on brand. Anyway, adding to the conflict
was Great Britain's meddling in the
whole mess. It turns out that they had
not honored the agreement in the Treaty
of Paris to evacuate their posts on the
western border. But, don't worry. What
they did instead was to arm American
Indians and encourage them to attack
American settlements in the Ohio River
Valley. And Spain pulled the same dirty
trick further south by arming Creeks and
Cherokees who used those weapons to
resist American westward expansion. But,
hey, if there's one thing you do not do
to Big Baby America is to make it harder
to migrate west. And so, in order to
address these increasing conflicts,
George Washington dispatched about 2,000
American soldiers into the Ohio country
to subdue the American Indians who were
harassing the US settlers. And there,
the troops met an alliance of American
Indians in the Battle of Fallen Timbers
in 1794. In the end, the US secured a
decisive victory, and that led to the
signing of the Treaty of Greenville. And
in this treaty, the defeated indigenous
alliance surrendered their claim to vast
tracts of land in the Ohio territory and
effectively opened it for American
settlement without resistance. The
treaty also made provision for the
defeated tribes to receive annual
payments from the federal government,
which effectively made them dependent on
such payments and thus more vulnerable
to further removal from their land in
later periods. And then after that, two
other developments occurred which got
the migration-stoked Americans so
excited that they peed in their pants a
little. But, you know,
just a little. The first was the signing
of Jay's Treaty in 1794. Now, to be
fair, a lot of Americans thought this
treaty was kind of a turd sandwich, but
it did do one thing that cleared the way
for more migration. Basically, Great
Britain agreed to withdraw its forces
from the western borderland. And as a
result, American Indians saw little hope
for resisting American encroachment on
their ancestral lands, and that may have
contributed to their concessions in the
Treaty of Greenville. And then, the
second development occurred 2 years
later when the United States ratified
the Pinckney Treaty with Spain. Now,
this agreement formally recognized the
borders between the US and Spanish
territory, while also opening the port
of New Orleans and the Mississippi River
to US merchants. And that was just fine
to the Americans because this treaty
effectively ended Spanish opposition to
US westward expansion in the south,
while also making it easier for
Americans to transport goods along the
Mississippi River. Okay, now the other
big part of this topic has to do with
the expansion of slavery during this
period. You see, southern planters were
eager to migrate west in search of new
land to plant. That's because
high-demand crops like tobacco and
cotton sucked the nutrients right out of
the soil. Therefore, in order to keep
pace, especially with increasing
European demands for those goods,
planters began to migrate westward in
large numbers. And as you might have
guessed, as they migrated, they went
ahead and brought slavery with them, and
that started brewing a different
conflict in the new nation. You see, in
the northern states, a growing movement
for the abolition of slavery began to
take shape. Some argued for abolition on
account of their religious convictions
against the brutality of slavery, folks
like the Quakers and the Mennonites.
Then, others were motivated by
enlightenment ideas about the equality
of all people. But, to be absolutely
clear, it wasn't just the northerners
who were getting a little squeamish
about slavery. No, even some prominent
southerners were getting some rumbles in
their tummies about this inhumane
institution. For example, folks like
James Madison and Thomas Jefferson, both
of whom relied on enslaved blacks for
their wealth, were uneasy about the
institution and hoped that it would
gradually pass away as more and more
immigrants arrived who could work for
low wages. But, I'm sad to tell you that
did not in fact occur. You see, in 1793,
Eli Whitney invented the cotton gin,
which greatly increased the efficiency
with which cotton could be processed.
And in doing so, cotton productivity
rapidly increased, and so did the demand
for the raw material. And so, that
development led to a sharp increase in
the demand for enslaved blacks to work
the cotton fields, and that meant
slavery became even more entrenched in
the south. And because their economy
depended so heavily on the growth and
export of cotton, many southern planters
refused to consider any notion of
abolition. And that commitment therefore
began to reveal intense regional
disagreement over the presence of
slavery in the United States. But, I
should mention that at this point, the
general opinion about slavery in the
south was that it was a necessary evil.
And that's important because in the next
period, we're going to see that opinion
shift dramatically so that slavery in
the south was considered a positive
good. And that makes me wonder if we're
going to see any further conflict over
this issue later in the course. So,
who knows? Okay, you can click here to
keep watching my other Unit 3 videos, or
you can click here to grab my APUSH
Heimler review guide, which has
everything you need to study as fast as
possible. I appreciate you stopping by,
and I'll catch you on the flip-flop. I'm
out.